Well, welcome to ApushUS, y'all. I am
Steve Heimler, your bald bearded gap
tooth guide through AP US history. And I
reckon we'll get started by talking
about the indigenous makeup of the
Americas before European contact. And
so, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. Now,
probably the very most important thing
you need to remember for this topic is
that before all those wy diseaseladen,
pantaloonwearing Europeans showed up to
the Americas, the people who already
lived here were very different from one
another, which is to say indigenous
peoples were diverse. And it shouldn't
surprise you because every other dang
continent in the world is home to
diverse peoples as well. People who
speak different languages and have
developed different cultures. Like if I
show up to France and say, "Hey, aren't
y'all basically the same as the
British?" Well, then I'm going the right
way for a good oldfashioned French
smackb. So, in the same way, the
indigenous groups that populated the
Americas were very different from each
other in language and culture and
customs and economics, etc. Some groups
lived in nomadic hunter gatherer bands
while others lived in massive cities
while others lived in semi-permanent
settlements. And while geography did
play a significant role in those
differences, and we'll get to that in
just a second, one other factor that
often determined whether indigenous
groups moved around in small groups or
clumped up into larger settlements was
the cultivation of maze. And I'll tell
you, if you've never had it, that stuff
is amazing. It's just
Sorry, that's
that joke usually kills at the
horicultural history conferences.
Anyway, maize was first cultivated in
central Mexico around 5,000 B.CE. and it
became a staple crop of various peoples
throughout the Americas. And once these
people realized that you could grow food
in the ground to stuff in people's mouth
holes, they developed complex societies
centered on sedentary agriculture, which
is a fancy way of saying they stopped
moving around and planted their hind
parts in one spot. And hey, before I
tell you about the fabulous effects of
maze cultivation, let me just mention my
a pushheimler review guide, which has
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May.
It's got exclusive unit review videos
that are not here on YouTube, metric
buttloads of practice questions, and an
AI Heimler bot that will answer all your
questions and grade all your exams. and
a generous helping of SAS from this guy.
Anyway, the link is in the description,
so get that clicky finger out and have a
look. Anyway, the cultivation of maze
had four effects that you're going to
need to remember. First, it led to
economic development because trade
networks developed between these
societies. Second, it led some groups
into permanent settlements since
agriculture can't exactly be done by
nomadic groups who are always on the
move. Third, the cultivation of maze led
to advanced irrigation techniques. Now,
irrigation just describes the methods by
which humans divert natural water
sources toward their crops. It's kind of
a big deal because the better people get
at irrigation, the more food they can
grow and therefore the more people their
society can sustain. And then fourth,
the cultivation of maze led to social
diversification. And that just means
that as a settlement and society becomes
bigger and more complex, labor becomes
more specialized and social hierarchies
and put in place, which means that some
people become more important than the
others. Okay, so let's go ahead and get
some specific examples of this diversity
of peoples in the Americas. And just for
poops and giggles, we'll start right
here in the Great Basin and Great Plains
regions. Now, remember what I said
earlier. Yes, maize was a pretty big
deal, but geography also played a
massive role in how various people
groups organized their lives and
society. So here in the Great Basin and
the Great Plains, the climate is about
as hot and dry as the devil's armpit.
And so indigenous groups living here
responded to their environment by
developing mobile or nomadic lifestyles.
And just in case you have an image of
that mobility being facilitated by
horses, those have not been introduced
yet, but don't worry, they're coming
with the Europeans soon. Anyway, that
mobility meant in general that many
groups who lived here were smaller
societies that lived far apart from one
another since they needed a great deal
of land to hunt and gather. For example,
meet the Ute people. They lived in
groups of about 20 to 100 which
consisted of extended family groups and
they moved throughout the region on a
seasonal basis while living in mobile
shelters like animal skin tepee. The ute
men were typically responsible for
hunting animals like deer and antelope
and rabbits while women gathered berries
and roots. Additionally, groups like the
Ute moved according to the season so
that they didn't deplete the resources
in any one area. So again, their
environment largely shaped the way that
they lived. And now let's head over to
the east coast and see what kind of
diversity we can find over there. So in
general, indigenous groups who lived in
these areas tended to create much larger
and complex societies than hunter
gatherer groups because their
environment was much better for farming.
And you're going to need to know an
example of each and you know I'm in the
mood to give them to you. So first here
we have various groups that taken
together are known as the Mississippian
cultures. and we'll just focus on one of
them, namely the Hopewell people. Now,
because of the abundance of rich soil
around the Mississippi and Ohio river
valleys, the Hopewell people were able
to exist in large towns, about 4,000 to
6,000 in population. And due to their
proximity to large rivers, the Hopewell
got their trade on with other indigenous
groups as far away as Canada and
Florida. To which I say, what now? Once
maze cultivation became their way of
life, the Hopewell civilization became
more complex, including a social
hierarchy in which the elite gained more
control over the common laborers. And
they were also mound builders. And these
things were pretty massive. And I'm not
just mentioning mounds for poops and
giggles. Those massive structures give
you an insight into their society,
namely their religious traditions and
the various ways that they organized
labor on a large scale and some sort of
elite class. And I would be remiss if I
didn't mention the largest of the
Mississippian cities, namely Cahokia,
which had a population of somewhere
between 10 and 20,000 people. And why is
that, my dear people? because their
environment dictated fabulous
agricultural growth which meant more
people could live together and their
society could become more complex. Okay,
the second group I want to introduce you
to lived here in the northeast and
they're known as the irra. Now they were
semi- sedentary relying on the
cultivation of maze and other staple
crops for survival and then the abundant
timber in the region gave them the
materials to construct the main
infrastructure of their life together
namely the long house. Now, in case it's
not obvious, a long house was a, you
know, long house, which is a great name
for it because it would be much more
confusing if what they actually lived in
were, you know, short toasted. Anyway,
in these long houses, multiple
generations of Irakcoy families lived
together, sometimes up to 200 folks.
Additionally, these people were
responsible for creating the Irakcoy
Confederacy, which was an alliance of
multiple indigenous groups in the area,
including all of these folks right here.
And that confederacy formed a council of
representatives to help settle beefs
between rival groups that would
otherwise lead to war. and they
facilitated trade partnerships as well.
And then the third group I'll mention is
the Cherokees who made their lives along
the Atlantic coast. Now maze cultivation
reached them about 1,000 B.CE along with
beans and squash which meant that their
society was built around agriculture.
However, they would also qualify as
semi-edentary because men still hunted
for meat while women usually tended the
crops. In fact, like many other
indigenous groups, women had far more
social capital than their European
counterparts. In fact, many of their
cultures were matrinal, meaning that
power and possessions were passed down
through generations on the mother's
side, not the fathers. And now, let's go
visit our friends on the Pacific coast
of North America. And there are two
distinct regions over here. Now,
societies in the northwest and present
day California didn't generally practice
agriculture, but instead they were
hunters and gatherers. So, I'm assuming
that the comparative thinking part of
your brain is all like, okay, so they
were just like the youth, hunters and
gatherers and nomadic and whatnot.
>> It's like I'm reading your mind, isn't
it? But no, that is a similarity with
the Great Basin and Great Plains people.
But groups over here like the Chinuk and
the Schumash built permanent
settlements. But how could they have
done that? Says you since settled
societies were mostly associated with
agriculture. Well says I because of the
abundance of food they were able to get
from the oceans and the surrounding
environment. That meant that they could
live in large permanent settlements not
supported by traditional agriculture and
trade. And that makes them different
from the indigenous groups that lived in
the arid regions and similar to those
that lived in the more fertile
agricultural regions. Well, okay. Click
here to watch my other videos from unit
one. And click here to grab my A Push
Himler review guide, which has
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May.
And I'll catch you on the flip-flop.